and now let's look at the second
possible right update optimization which
is about reducing the number of bus
rights so after we added our dirty bit
what we got is that the memory now gets
relatively few rights only those rights
that are coming from replacements and
also the memory no longer needs to
respond to all the reads but the bus
still gets all of the traffic for all of
the rights every single right will need
to go on the bus and broadcast the value
so now the bus which sees all of the
rights will become the bottleneck in
this system
because every single write from every
single core ends up going to the bus and
the bus can only take so much the bus
broadcasts for rights that are needed to
update other copies of the data need to
happen because this is a write-update
protocol it needs to update other copies
of the data but the optimization we can
do is about the rights that do not need
to update anybody so we will add another
bit called the shared bit to each block
in each cache and that bit will tell us
whether the block is shared with others
or not let's see how things would work
suppose we read a here we get this valid
not dirty but for the shared bit we need
to know whether others also have this
block or not for this purpose
we add a line to the bus when a reed
goes to memory others snoop this read
and if they have that same block in the
cache then they pull the shared line to
one if nobody pulls the shared line to
one then it will remain at zero so for
this particular block because this is
the first read nobody pulls the shared
line to one so the block we know is not
shared this is the tag and let's say
we're at six now let's see what happens
when this processor writes to a and
let's say it puts a value of seventeen
there it's a Miss we broadcast both the
right and the value the first time and
we see now that somebody is writing
and this cash here snoops that right and
those two things one it now knows that
the block is shared because somebody is
accessing it now second it updates the
value third it pulls this line to one so
that this cash knows the block is shared
and now it has the Block in the dirty
State with the value of 17 so so far
this has behaved exactly as it should
without the shared line and without the
shared bit so what's the benefit of the
shared bits well the benefit is that now
this cash if it wants to write again it
sees that the shared bit is one which
means that it does need to broadcast
same as before so the broadcast will
happen exactly as before if there is
another sharer because we need to update
that sharer to the new value for the
data the benefit of the shared it is in
that if this block reads let's say B and
gets a value of 2 here and it's valid
and it's not dirty and it is that so far
nobody has B so sharing is 0 here and
then wants to write 5 to be it checks
the shared bit here and because we know
that nobody else has this block we can
write the value here make the thing
dirty because the memory is no longer
up-to-date but because the shared bit
stays at 0 meaning we are the only one
who has it
we don't do a bus right here so as long
as some block is being accessed only by
one core it's no longer gonna broadcast
all of the rights meanwhile this core
could be having in a non shared State
for example Block C and it can write
anything in once there you can write 17
then 65 etc so B and C because they
belong to only one core at this time
will not do bus rights while a will do
bus rights so we still get the right
update behavior when there is sharing
but now we avoid rights going to the bus
when there is no sharing
this can happen a lot for example B
could be something that belongs to the
stack of course zero seek would be
something that is on the stack of cor
one so naturally we will be just pushing
and popping things to our own stack and
never really needing to broadcast the
updates somewhere else but for data that
is actually shared we still get exactly
the same right update behavior as before
so this optimization will save us a lot
of Rights on the bus it will save us all
of the rights that are not necessary to
maintain coherence among multiple copies
of the same block in different caches